becoming a full-time Trader seems like
the promised land for many people
learning to trade but something I've
noticed is that many Traders believe the
difficult part is getting yourself to
that point and then Things become
straightforward but the reality is a bit
different there are so many benefits of
trading full-time but there are also
major challenges that you don't have to
deal with until you get to that point
being aware of these challenges will not
only help you navigate this transition
much better but also give you a chance
to prepare in a more realistic way while
you're still working towards that goal
so with that in mind I want to go
through some major challenges that
you'll face as a full-time Trader and
these are based on my own experience and
from helping loads of Traders over the
years so here are the three things I
believe that full-time Traders should
never do you can't control what happens
in the markets it doesn't matter how
great you are at trading that's just an
undeniable fact okay I guess I better
include a bit of a caveat here that is
unless you control the asset you have
enough Capital to dve Drive price
movements or your name's ninda saral I'm
going to assume it's a no to all three
of those so it's always a good idea to
segment things into two categories
things you can control and things you
can't the market itself falls into the
latter category we can control our
trading system our entry criteria our
position size and a bunch of other
things but we can't control the markets
therefore it's inevitable that you'll
have better performance in some months
than you will in others you can have the
greatest Trading system but if the
market isn't presenting the right
opportunities you're not going to have
any trades likewise even if you're
taking trades with a positive expectancy
as you should you still don't know
whether the outcome of each individual
trade will be a profit or a loss even as
a profitable Trader you could easily
have a losing month after having a
string of losses this is just part and
parcel of trading but this can be a
problem for Traders who treat their
monthly returns as if it's a monthly
salary from a regular job I mean what
what do you think is going to happen if
you're getting towards the end of the
month and you haven't made enough money
yet what if you're at break even or even
worse what if you're in a loss what do
you think will happen to your decision-
making you suddenly have a lot more
pressure and you're much more likely to
take bigger and maybe even inappropriate
risks you'll probably begin overtrading
experiencing fomo and risking higher
percentages of your Capital to try and
reach that return that you need and then
once you're actually in a trade you'll
have heightened loss aversion and make
decis decisions that deviate from your
plan so these are basically the same
sorts of issues that you experience when
you risk too much money on a single
trade and that's because if you're
relying on your monthly return there is
more risk on each trade now I get
messages quite often from Traders asking
about this transition to full-time
trading and they'll tell me I have this
much money to trade with and if I hit
the same returns that I've been getting
recently I'll have enough money to live
off but that's not quite the right way
to think about it instead you should
have enough money set aside to cover
your costs for a prolonged period of
time regardless of what returns you make
in your trading account so this means
dividing your Capital into money for
your trading account and money that's
not put at risk that you use to cover
your costs then you can take withdrawals
from your trading account less often
once you've built up a big enough return
to cover the withdrawal amount without
wiping out any growth that you've
achieved in the trading account you know
living paycheck to paycheck based on
trading returns is a recipe for disaster
so to give you some context I quit my
job in banking in 2012 to go full-time
with my trading and this was a
relatively easy decision to make because
by that point I'd already made well over
£400,000 in profits from the markets so
that meant I wasn't going to be relying
on my trading account each month to
cover my living costs I had more than
enough money for both I could make
withdrawals once or twice a year to fund
my living cost account I wouldn't have
to rely on the monthly returns but don't
worry you don't necessar neily need to
achieve that amount of capital instead
since things like prop trading are more
accessible these days you can use things
like that to supplement your trading
capital for example one of our members
managed to get around £800,000 in
capital through prop funding so by
taking this approach it means you can
just focus on saving up enough money to
cover your living costs without relying
on your trading returns before you make
that move to trading full-time you know
I have to say this next one is a problem
I struggled with for many years without
realizing it I had this subconscious
belief that if I'm a Trader it means I'm
only working when I'm in a trade
therefore if I had a trading session
without taking any trades it just felt
like I'd done something wrong like I'd
been unproductive in some way now it
wasn't such an issue when I was trading
part-time because I could go for weeks
without opening any trades simply
because I was focused on other things so
I was used to having days go by without
taking an opportunity but this all
changed once trading was my full-time
job if I didn't open a trade during a
session I'd actually feel guilty about
it I'd feel as if I was failing like I
just wasted an entire day now over time
this would lead me to start extending my
trading session times or start following
more markets neither of which would lead
to my best performance but here's
something you realize after years of
experience or hopefully you can start to
understand it sooner that if you're
analyzing the markets and doing
everything that you should be doing but
you don't find an opportunity you have
still been working your job as a Trader
doesn't only involve opening trades
that's only one part of the role in fact
you'll also start to realize as I did
that great trading is just as much about
the times that you don't trade as the
times that you do your performance is
defined by your long-term results not
each individual session so understanding
accepting and expecting this before you
make that shift to full-time trading
will mean that you put less pressure on
yourself that leads to you taking the
the wrong actions things like
overtrading or taking bad trade
opportunities if I could go back to 2012
and give myself one piece of advice it
would be this if you want your trading
career to be sustainable and to perform
at your best stick to a consistent
routine not doing this caused me big big
problems that I eventually had to fix
including serious issues with my health
and that's no joke now when you have a
regular job you're forced into a
somewhat consistent routine because of
the set hours that you have to work then
as soon as you become your own boss as a
full-time Trader there's no one stopping
you from working whatever hours you wish
there's always a market open somewhere
that you could be trading if you want to
now there are three common ways that
this can become a problem you could work
too much not work enough or not work
consistently now my main problem has
always been working too much as I
started to make great money from Trading
I became a caricature of the expression
timing as money I literally lived My
Life by that I didn't want to go out
anywhere and if I did I was still
following the markets I didn't want to
sleep when I did sleep I had the laptop
open right beside the bed so I could
check the markets when I woke up in the
night I barely even ate I wanted to
spend as much time in front of the
charts as I could because missing an
opportunity would mean potentially
missing out on more money now because of
this unhealthy lifestyle that I was
living my health deteriorated rapidly
and I had several serious symptoms
including a terrible infection so I was
rushed to an emergency clinic the
doctors did all sorts of tests and at
one point they were convinced I had
diabetes but it turns out I was just
severely run down and suffering from
chronic stress and I talked about all of
this and all of my experiences around
that time in a video that you can click
up here to watch you know trust me it's
so easy to fall onto this slippery slope
of thinking more trading time equals
more money but in reality your
performance per hour will be so far from
your Peak you'll be making more mistakes
and nothing nothing about it will be
sustainable in fact Studies have shown
how bad sleep can be disastrous for our
trading in ways that we're not
consciously aware of and again there's a
video up here you can watch to
understand more about that but then at
the complete opposite end of the
spectrum you may actually find that you
end up working much less maybe not
working enough since you're not being
held accountable by work colleagues or
your boss your work sessions might
gradually reduce and reduce as you
realize that you could be doing other
things you're likely to be working from
home so it means you have to constantly
battle with all the usual distractions
while not having anyone there to tell
you off for missing your day of work
it's only you being accountable to
yourself but you know a far more common
situation is for Traders to spend a good
amount of time in the markets but
following an irregular routine it's kind
of like the cycle that teenagers go
through during school holidays you start
going to bed later then because of that
you start waking up later and before you
know it you don't have set work times
you just get started started whenever
you wake up and finish when you feel
like it now there are many reasons why
this is bad for your trading not only is
an inconsistent sleep routine just as
bad as not sleeping for long enough each
night but the actual skill aspect is
going to suffer as well without
following the markets at set times
you'll lack a lot of important implicit
knowledge and since a big part of
trading is about being consistent how
can you achieve that if everything in
your life is in flux you will experience
your best performance and be much more
likely to have a sustainable long-term
career as a Trader if you stick with a
set routine each day as boring as it
seems if you achieve consistency in your
everyday life you'll be much more likely
to experience consistency in the markets
remember being a full-time Trader is a
job yes you have a lot more freedom but
you should still hold yourself
accountable in the same way you would if
you were reporting to someone else so
these are just some of the challenges
that you'll face as a full-time Trader
once you make the transition I'm sure
you'll encounter many more problems that
you'll have to solve but don't let this
dishearten you achieving success in any
career involves experiencing challenges
and learning to overcome them that's how
you continue to grow and how you gain
wisdom now in most cases the best way to
solve a problem is to think about it
logically find the root cause of the
problem and find ways to overcome or
mitigate that and if you want to know
more of the most important insights that
I think Traders need to succeed check
out my free training that's Linked In
description box below thanks for
watching